all right uh we're at
J I
think yeah
okay uh by the
way in in English we call stream of
Consciousness or we say just
somebody not connected sentences really
they're just this
loong uh this particular loong this
seventh part of this loo is really just
random advice okay
probably some graduate student in a
university can connect them in a
doctoral thesis but it looks like they
are just um random advices okay so
here's another one okay and they are
short and sweet and by the way we will
not
stay here we are learning Boda we are
learning how to develop bod the main uh
class is
lo the the main topic is d uh making
ourselves and others equal and then
exchanging oursel with others and we're
almost finished with
it uh and it's been 13 years and now
we're going to soon I think in this week
maybe uh we will reach the six
Perfections okay we will start on the
six perfection infections and that's
kind of the ultimate goal of the Alum
room so uh if grandpa doesn't tell too
many
stories uh probably we can read
okay uh
CH that's the that's the little piece
from the loo from the book okay
CH and say again as Gibson mentioned it
means measure what's the measure
that you have finished uh in Sanskrit
it's ma like PR and it means measure the
word meter comes from that like
that when it stops you're finished okay
and that's the kind of advice that this
Lo he just give you these
little songs you know it's like okay
when it stops that's the measure and
you're like what when it stops you're
ready okay when it stops you're ready
okay so what's it
mean if your meditation topic is your
own death okay if you are dedicating
some effort and some time to planning
and thinking about your own death
okay
and means
don't get too attached to the things in
this world okay you can't keep them you
won't remember them 10 minutes after you
die okay all your stock accounts and
your bank accounts and your cars and
even
Tesla you cannot remember about 10
minutes after you die okay you won't
remember anything okay you won't all of
it will be gone
okay let it go
before you lose it okay that's a nice
philosophy Gesa is it bad for a Buddhist
to have a Tesla no it's very good okay
everyone should have a Tesla it's fun
Buddhist responsibility is to have fun
okay that's your practice is to have fun
and if it's in
1953 Chevrolet truck have fun me and
Bill are working on a truck
uh have fun uh with your life but don't
be afraid to lose it okay have fun uh
you can have things it's
okay you deserve them if the world is
coming from seeds you earned it you paid
for it already Okay you paid the seeds
already the paying getting the car at
the Tesla dealer is just a detail you
already paid the money when you reach
there before you reach
you you're paying in seeds right and
that's fine that's fine you cannot give
the seeds Away by the way so you might
as well take the Tesla okay you can give
Grandpa a ride okay that's happens lo
jongi I will tell you a Tesla story but
I think the person won't like it
so see I can keep my
mouth
okay
when you stop worrying about things by
the way the three levels of line
practice right they start with
death okay the three levels of Lan
practice start with death okay if you're
not ready to
die uh you're not even in l you're in
the wrong
room okay if you're not ready to die
you're in the wrong room right now this
you can't get into this room if you're
not practicing your death or if you're
not getting used to it you you you
didn't reach the long Rim class okay
uh let it go you know let let go the
things of this life before you lose them
let go of them if you can let go of a
Tesla you deserve one
one okay if you can let go of a Tesla
you deserve one we were at the Mandarin
Hotel oh my God there's we walk out
there's three rolls-royces I didn't even
ever see a Rolls-Royce
recently and uh I don't know Shia ping
cheated me she said oh this car is all
for you g you know you just pick one I'm
like Bill there wasn't any old Chevys so
I'd let it go okay
um you can have a Tesla it's fine it's
wonderful but but if you can die without
worrying about it that's that's it that
is fine it's okay have a
Tesla there's nothing in Buddhism say
you cannot have fun there's no there's
no Sutra that says Buddhist cannot have
fun there's no sutas say Buddhist cannot
have a
Tesla you can search John Brady's
database there's no s like that
okay
uh okay you can have it's okay but you
cannot but you have to be ready to die
and and give the Tesla to somebody else
okay there's a joke in the
monastery the teach the student asked
the teacher is it okay to have a Tesla I
said yeah it's okay but then the later
the Tesla will have to look for a new
owner the Tesla will go and look for a
new owner because you will die he say
yeah you could get a Tesla but make sure
the Tesla knows how to find a new owner
uh otherwise he's going to be lonely the
Tesla will be lonely after you die okay
all
right so we have
to get used
to Doc chinen stopping this attitude of
taking care of myself first okay and by
the way I I'm old man and uh I can tell
you if you give up this idea of taking
yourself taking care of yourself first
okay give up the just give it up now
don't wait till you're 70
and9 okay just give it up now okay this
attitude that you should take care of
yourself first it's not elegant by the
way Buddhism is elegant Buddhist
practice is elegant okay they have all
this Dior I I went to Christian deor I
made a
mistake I I went to Christen Dior store
because I'm looking for a dress for
Veronica you know I have this problem
right I go to Christian deal and I us
perfect dress you know and I'm like I
I'll take it you know and then they say
okay do you know the price I said it
doesn't matter I love her you know and
then they say Okay $5,000 then I'm
like this was in taiwana I think I said
wait you have a branch in New York City
right he said yeah I said I'll just pick
it up in New York uh otherwise I have to
carry it home and you know and I lucky I
canceled it okay so uh dark changing is
uh you can have those things but if you
stop this Habit to take care of yourself
first okay take care of other people
first you can wait until you're 50 you
can wait until you're 60 you can wait
until you're 70 sooner or
later you have to give up this thing of
taking care of your yourself first
sooner or later you got to give it up
okay I I give you permission keep it for
two more weeks then give it up whatever
is your age give it up now and then the
rest of your life is so easy so God dang
easy you know stop taking care of
yourself first take care of other people
first peacock peacock Behavior right
take care of other people first the
earlier you learn it the more relaxed
your life will be okay and they're more
fun much more fun uh to take care of
other people first okay much much more
fun and don't wait for 50 years 60 years
to to find out how fun it is okay try it
now just take care of other people first
everything everything you know who goes
to the toilet first oh you guys
go you know take care of other people
first okay and get in the habit just
make a habit and your whole life is a
lot of fun after that your whole life
don't wait until you're really old to
take care of other people first do it
now otherwise you're not going to have
fun you you're cheating yourself okay
it's so fun to take care of other people
it's really really fun okay so don't
don't make that mistake okay don't be
selfish okay it's a big mistake it's not
fun you think are taking care of
yourself you're not uh when you are take
care of yourself first you are not
taking care of yourself okay when you're
taking care of other people you're
having really fun all the time all the
time and nothing's difficult because you
don't care if you lose anything you see
I mean you don't care if someone else
takes it or someone else gets it you're
like okay that's what I'm here for I'm a
someone else should get it first person
okay that's my job what's your job
people ask me on the plane what's your
job I said don't even ask me you know
it's too confusing I'm a someone else go
first take career you know that's my job
you know just it's so fun it's so much
more fun okay taking care of yourself
first is a lot of it's a big hustle and
it's a lot of trouble okay take care of
other people it's fun it's real fun fun
okay so just try try it for two weeks
see how it feels and you can see okay
it's much much more
fun to see people's face when you give
them you know
hey last week I gave somebody
$64,000 they're like wow and
like you know and it's fun okay it's
more fun all right all right
uh J means a sign that you have
developed loo okay there's five signs
that you have developed lojo you're
successful lojo person okay J means uh
five signs that you you are pretty good
in your Lo your Lo is pretty good
okay there's five of
them
then he gives them a name and he
describes them okay so the name of the
first one is uh Cho
say
cho
cho only Gibson knows the Sanskrit
for
Sans
tus yeah
tus uh the Mandarin in Shenzhen has a
tus bar and I went there because I
thought I can practice
tus uh tus in Sanskrit means
uh
difficult difficult meditation or deep
deep super deep super difficult
meditation is called uh or practice is
called
K tapus okay in Portugal Spain it means
little snack
food I like both of them
okay what's the definition of the great
[Music]
M someone hurts you and you don't get
irritated for one
second someone hurts you and you don't
get irritated for one second then that's
mahat
it's very you want to hear a bad
joke you have to say yes or I will not
tell
it okay if you don't want to hear gisha
say bad thing close your ears
now okay uh there's a very famous uh
saying that the highest tus is to not
get angry when someone hurts you so
tapus means spiritual
hard practice in India you have to burn
your body or you have to jump off a
bridge or you have to put a knife to
your hand or then you're a tough guy it
means tough guy tus means tough guy
you're a tough guy spiritual tough guy
okay and then uh the most famous
spiritual tough guy Shanti DEA said is
uh you can keep your patience you don't
get angry you don't get upset so there a
famous Story the guy is walking outside
of
Plaza and uh he meet a a big tantrica in
Tibet they have long long hair and
should be braided and should be they
didn't take a bath for a few weeks and
and they are have this dominer you know
D ding ding ding and they're
like then secret diamond diamond way guy
Diamond way master actually usually they
have no training at all but so there's
this diamond way
master and uh he's meditating by the
side of the road and then the guy's like
H and he whisper in his ear he says what
are you doing the guy
says I'm
meditating
oh what's the
meditation
patience never get
angry wow eat then gu
what he say you're not meditating on
P famous joke
okay M monk joke is kind of weird okay
they they can't have a they don't have
any sex joke for example so they have to
make joke about tus okay famous k chimbo
it means uh when someone really hurts
you you're like yeah
okay okay not very exciting you know you
are not jumping off a clear for you are
not meditating for 12 hours or something
like that someone hurts you and you're
like yeah okay suang went home I don't
know yeah in Arizona it's you can drive
a car
and big truck follows you dangerous and
you're like yeah
okay okay
okayo SBA chimo means great warrior
great warrior okay Warrior what's a
great warrior in lojong
practice dark Shen
chimba uh Gibson this is the comparative
instrumental it's kind of rare okay you
use the instrumental s s case do
and it's comparative it's so what's it
mean rather than you others okay other
than you others okay dark CH chenin
means take care of others first before
yourself take care of others more than
yourself take care of others instead of
yourself okay if you learn it you will
have a happy life and you will have fun
every single day you will have fun okay
if you can learn learn it I guarantee
you you'll be you have fun your rest of
your life
okay I'm I'm I get really sad when I see
people who don't know about it I I feel
sad because I feel God they could have
fun all the time they just take care of
themselves first you know take care of
other people just try it and it the rest
of your life he's going to have fun
super fun and successful also you're not
giving them anything the more you give
up for other people the more you get
duh my my ballet teacher taught me duh
duh means don't be stupid don't be
stupid the more you give to other
people the more Rich you become okay and
then you can give away when day was it
day before your stay 65,000 this you
know and then it's going to come more
okay uh
okay get used to it and do it you're not
losing anything you're not U risking
anything there's no risk to take care of
other people you're not risking just
give and it it will keep coming back and
back I I don't know where's my bank
account I don't know the number I don't
know the passcode only one living person
knows it she's back there and uh I
always have to call her I say Where's my
bank account well you have this one this
one this then I said what's the password
she says G I don't give you the password
you're GNA lose it you know so she takes
care of everything okay like that just
keep giving okay and and you not only
have a lot of bank accounts you got
someone to take care of the bank account
and you don't have to think about the
bank account and that's a real rich man
okay you don't have to think about the
bank account somebody else worry she
worried about the bank account she
probably she's balancing it right now
okay all right
uh you never give up uh doing the 10
Dharma activities okay easy way uh
there's several definitions of these 10
easy way is the six Perfections and
there four ways of taking care of other
people
okay easy way there's another definition
I think in the
Abid okay
uh okay uh that's called great PR
practitioner
uh okay if you avoid hurting anybody at
all completely avoid hurting other
people tra
she do then we say you are what do you
call peaceful you are peaceful you you
have a peaceful mind if you don't hurt
other people okay that's peace that's
peace
right d Cho you are the great Vania
holder okay
DBA is very important word in our
tradition they keep their V keep the van
okay uh
uh
now in
shenen we they asked gisha to do shua
some
calligraphy uh and they gave it as a
gift to a Pung
M
right and here it
is okay this is the word this is the
first word I chose now now
okay
say this is here is a very very
important word okay very very important
word okay
um NJ means yoga it's the Tibetan
translation for yoga okay
NJ is the Tibetan translation for yoga n
is
yog female yoga Master female yoga
Master V
yogini is the greatest Buddhist angel in
history okay and uh so
NJ here he's making a joke okay and it's
very subtle and the man the monk who
wrote this book The the editor of the
book is CH R he's born in 1901 passed
away in
1981 he's my teacher's
teacher uh who wrote this book who wrote
down this book and he's the greatest
writer in modern history great great
great writer unbelievable writer and you
are that lineage he's your great great
grandpa I'm your
grandpa Ken remember your I'm your papa
K is your grandpa and CH is your great
grandpa and you are direct lineage of CH
you you should study this book because
your great-grandfather wrote it down and
your great great-grandfather taught it
and that's your lineage okay even you
don't want it you are okay I'm sorry if
you're in this room uh your lineage isup
which is the teacher of the Dilma okay
and great
great great great
scholar but he's famous for his kindness
he's not so famous for his scholarship
he's fa famous for being a nice person
and a kind person and uh his beautiful
face I'll I'll show you a
picture his face is beautiful you know
he has a face kind face okay uh anyway
uh
they wrote this book n n Jona here those
great writers are making a joke okay
they
say
say J jorda means you make a connection
okay jorda means you make a connection
the Sanskrit is huge or yoga okay yoke
of two oxin and things like that okay so
Jah Joy means to connect connection now
means
uh that's the crucial word here when the
tatan translated yoga they didn't just
use the word for connection they used
the word now now
means uh
Mar you want to
explain
yeah Stanley taught it last week and
shinin these two guys taught it last
week you see this uh it's not Jackie
Chen it's the other guy
huh kind of Bruce Lee but who's the
other
one jley yeah jley when he fights some
guy you know
the the person who's not a Wu Master
martial arts master if they're not
master the movie is very long you know
boom boom boom bo you
know a real real Wu Kung Fu Master he's
like then the
guy and then the guy fall down dead and
dead like that you know just
go and
they you know just get there's some
point in your body I don't know where it
is luckily my brother doesn't know
uh they just do like this and you die
okay that's called
now okay it means a
exact point you know and you don't go
and jump up and down yeah there's
there's picture I like this picture I
love the picture he wrote this book he
wrote down this book for his teacher
teacher gave a
talk and uh he was the
the writer he was the editor it took I
think it took him about 20
years uh to finish this book and it's a
masterpiece it's it's the greatest book
in the Tibetan language in the modern
language it's the greatest book yeah and
[Music]
uh he lived I live next to him for six
month he's in the next
building and uh I thought I don't want
to bother him so I didn't ask to meet
him and uh and then he passed away and I
told my teacher and he yelled at me for
like one hour
stupid you you stayed next to him for
six months and you didn't go see his
face you know you stupid and
uh my teacher has one name for me and
that's the one so anyway uh n Jona means
uh the word
yoga in in tibetan is precise practice
in in the military they call a precision
air strike Precision bum it goes to the
exact uh half a meter or and and that's
nelma that means nelma so real
practice great practice
means effective and minimum effort
okay super effective and you're not
jumping up and down for half an hour
kicking and punching and you're just
like okay and then you get to be a
Buddha something like that okay what is
it what's what's the
man taking care of yourself first then
cut it you know like think and then then
your life is smooth okay I I don't
know what's the most frustrating thing
about about being 70 number one your
body falls apart even you do yoga your
body falls apart it falls apart slower
it's good okay that's that's the second
most frustrating thing the most
frustrating thing is that you figured
out life and No One Believes
you you tell younger people you know you
grab Genie like
this I figured it out you know and she's
like what G you say stop taking care of
your so take care of other people she's
like nice KLA nice okay just let
go okay you know uh but if you can
really do it you you're gonna be so
you're gonna have so much fun okay just
take care of other people first in the
beginning it's a little bit
uh hard you know like serve other people
first let other people go first
everything do for other people first in
the beginning it's a a little bit
difficult and then and then suddenly
everything is beautiful because you are
making great seeds all the time you are
making great seed we went with Sonia to
the she's at the airport she and eager
are the
same you see his shoulders it's like
that you know she can also do what you
do when we go to kia he picks up
everybody's luggies like five people
luggies he pick up at the same time and
I never saw it again until son can't we
travel with her and she's she can do it
also I guess it's from from having kids
or something I don't know but uh anyway
that's that's Precision practice
Precision practice you know don't waste
your time on 55 practices just take care
of other people first and that's like
air air strike precision air strike he
uses the word and and he's making a big
joke it's a big pun if you don't know
scripture you miss it okay he's he's
hiding the word for yoga here he's
hiding it here it's very beautiful okay
all right and he's hiding
mahata in the same sentence it's very
beautiful yeah okay last
one oh that makes you a nail drop a
chimle that makes you a great Yogi okay
if
you if you hit the
how do you say if you hit the killing
point in your practice and you kill your
Habit to take care of yourself first
then you're a yogi and it's a joke it's
a pun because the word is the
same okay you're a real Yogi got
it even if you don't get it just
nod my old students they are so
skillful there
some the worst ones they fall asleep in
the cloud and they start to
go those are the worst one you know and
better more experienced student they're
like
this and they are completely
asleep I me you got that you got that
thing about
yoga
there super high Yogi in gim M's
class they nod every few
minutes so they're like they are
completely asleep they're like they know
how to sleep with their eye
open then they know every one minute or
two minutes
they're okay so that's pretty prze
practice if you want to know
okay uh if you practice lojong you can
get this
F uh Tim I'm supposed to do
Q&A is it time it's Pas time right in
seven okay if anyone oh by the way we
reached a very interesting place in this
book uh when I was teaching in Mexico in
June
July uh there
are something like eight or nine great
teachers in Mexico very very good
teachers from guara and uh they just got
back from a tour they did a tour of like
five countries or something and they are
really
unbelievable teachers so when I went to
Mexico in
July I I brought them to my room and I
taught them the next
section and I said you guys teach it and
they taught it it's a I think it was
18 pieces of the lojo they took 18 of
the points and they taught the whole
thing and they did a great job they did
a really great job so uh and I'm really
happy what Peter and Maria are doing of
of having kids and grandkids and great
grandkids and you know I really I was on
a plane somewhere
lady s next to me you have any kids I
said yeah she said how many I said
84 and she's
like and I I think she's thinking about
some part of my body uh I don't know but
uh anyway maybe they have
more Peter okay all right uh any
question you guys
got
Tim oh so we're going to skip the next
part uh because they taught it already
and then we're going to go to the end of
the loog
okay thank you welcome amazing amazing
teaching uh which always
seems uh H the ccial
point okay in my mind I wanted to ask I
I I I have noticed that taking care of
other people first is twice in those
five
uh it comes in the second advice and in
the fourth advice think what why is that
yeah uh it's called D okay d andin means
uh
so before the time of the Buddha uh and
in the early years of
Buddhism there was a revolution in
Sanskrit uh in Sanskrit language before
that it was very
disorganized and there were many
different spellings and different
grammar rules and then somebody named
Panini uh he he
came and uh he made a a book of viaka he
made a book of grammar Sanskrit grammar
and it was so brilliant uh that everyone
followed in everybody accepted it and uh
no one writes any other Sanskrit the old
Sanskrit is gone the Vic Vic Sanskrit is
nobody can read it it's 5,000 years old
and nobody can read it it's in the old
style but the new style Panini is about
two couple thousand years old only 2,000
years old and he has a long list very
long list in the Tibetan translation
it's about 4,000 pages and um he has the
rules of Sanskrit and uh one of the
rules is called dupin dupin means uh a
great writer should never repeat
themselves and a great speaker should
never repeat
themselves they shouldn't repeat the
same thing over and over okay and in in
a
Sutra uh we should never repeat the same
point twice Sutra should move along with
fresh stuff and it nothing should be
repeated okay that if you do repeat it
uh you broke Panini you broke dup dupa
means to unnecessarily repeat something
okay
but uh so if a great writer does repeat
something like if Tre does repeat
something there's a reason there's a
deep deep reason okay and it's fun one
of my fun things is to find out the
reasons you know if someone like Pabon
repeats
something
uh a great student is supposed to go and
figure out why and there's always a
deeper reason okay like a great teacher
will never repeat something unless
there's a a purpose unless there's a
deep purpose okay people and as I
mentioned uh earlier you know I I was I
would never forget being accused of
teaching the
pen people say GUI Michael's getting old
and you say how do you know and they say
he keeps repeating the same thing like
those people in the nursing home you
know he keeps repeating the P he forgot
that he taught it last year and I I'm
not that old yet okay and there's a
reason why I repeating okay and uh it's
the same in the Lum room so something
fun is to read carefully those pages and
figure out why they repeated it because
it they're not they never make a mistake
like that they always have a reason I
was in my a car I got in a car with
another
student uh with my teacher and I was his
driver and everything else and uh you
know for over 20 years I was his to cook
his driver everything Gardener poooo
cleaner upper everything and uh so I
drive and and he's he says let's go to
the grocery store you know and uh I I
said wish you know he says turn left
here and it was the wrong instructions
we're supposed to turn
right he he said turn left here and I
just turn left my teacher says turn left
I turn left I don't worry about it you
know I don't say then the guy in back is
he's going crazy he's like no the gry
rests the right turn he start to try to
change the real I'm like
you know teachers say left there's a
reason you know and we went left we go
around the whole block and we see a
terrible accident you know on the
highway terrible people die you know and
and I'm
like
so if the if this book repeats something
there's a reason and it's fun to to try
to find the reason so that's your
assignment Ron you have to find the
reason okay and it's fun to figure out
why the teacher turned the wrong way
okay and and many times
uh it's fun to watch a new student get
frustrated about it you know guy's
always turning the wrong way shut up
there's a reason don't worry about it
okay
okay right other
uh that's a good place to stop actually
right
Tim right okay good all right uh M we
see you tomorrow and
uh
yeah lojo okay do do do tonight start
doing things for others first take care
of others first okay and I I don't know
it's very frustrating for old person
like just do that you're going to have
fun for your whole life and people are
like uhhuh uhhuh and then they don't do
it and it's very frustrating but if you
want to save yourself some trouble and
you want to have a happy life and a just
fun I'm not like a super peaceful guy I
don't sit there all the time oh you know
I like to get out and have a good dinner
with s you know I like to go out and
have fun and uh but if you take take
care of others first you have real fun
okay all right see you
tomorrow